next up we've got Matthias Lübken.
Oh I knew, I knew I want you told me how to pronounce it properly.
I wouldn't do this wrong.
Matthias Lübken. Matthias is an AI engineer
and founder who specializes in AI agents for business workflow and automation.
And his talk a piece of the pie embedding OpenClaw coding agent in your product.
Thank you.
Matthias.
Hello.
Hello, everyone.
Thanks a lot for having me
back in London. It's awesome.
Awesome to be here.
Yeah.
So I don't know how you guys have experienced this year,
but there was this OpenClaw thing happening in January,
and a friend of mine, we organized an event in Cologne
and a friend of mine called and says, Matthias, can you do a talk?
And I was like, yeah, sure.
But like, you know, let me, let me find something.
And I was digging through the code and I find this awesome
coding agent, which afterwards kind of like took over.
I feel it, at least.
Who heard about who heard about Pi.
Yeah, exactly.
That's what I'm talking about.
Two months ago, nobody would have raised her hand, including myself.
But now we're all here and experiencing it.
Yeah.
And I was like, digging through it.
And I built a prototype with it.
And that's what I'm going to talk with you about.
So basically my question is how do we design systems
which are able to deliver the same magic as OpenClaw as.
So this is me.
This is us, Evan and myself.
We're a small agency building systems.
We're building different tools for clients here in the UK and Germany.
And yeah, come to me
if you find the work interesting or want to chat about anything else.
So brief agenda.
First of all I'm going to talk a little bit like motivate this a little bit.
What what I mean by open Klaus magic.
Going to briefly introduce Pi and then an example.
Then I'm trying to you know this is an early talk.
So this looks very sophisticated.
It's not it's but it's basically trying to structure it a little bit.
But I have a couple of primitives I want to talk about that
helps us motivate this and kind of like
wrap our heads around it, some primitives and some patterns.
And I'm going to end the whole talk about malleable software.
But more on that later.
Cool. All right. So this is Peter
and this is OpenClaw.
And at some point in time he was this was in the early days.
It was basically had a chat interface was able to send check back and forth,
but more or less accidentally, he said the voice message to OpenClaw
and OpenClaw started thinking, right, these AI agents, they think.
And then it sent a text message back.
And I don't know how you guys feel, but when I see this,
there is a little bit magic into this.
Like, how does this work from the outside, right?
But as engineers, we're obviously looking behind the curtain.
So let's have a look.
So generally speaking, you know, very roughly right.
If you do these agents you have these general instructions.
And open Claw has these AGENTS.md and all this all these cool things.
But basically it's like okay,
your personal assistant, you do things and here are a bunch of a bunch of tools
like read right, edit file, bash commands.
So when it and this
this is is a simplification.
But I think you should get the get the idea.
So initially when it saw this this file.
So oh my god this is not a text file.
What do I do with it. Right.
And it used the usual Unix commands it and specter.
The file thought it was a wave file.
Then it tried to decode it
with a tool that it knew about whisper.
That didn't work.
And then somehow in its instructions, some words like, oh,
I could actually send this to OpenAI API.
There's actually one command missing that it actually was searching for a key
in order to send it. Right.
All of that did it in a loop again and again.
Again. This is oversimplification.
And at some point it got the goal completed.
And again,
I feel from the this is this is awesome because I understand now what happens.
But I want to reuse that that magic in my tools.
So very briefly. Right.
Coding agents are these agents who have these these tools that run in a loop.
And that's that's like the general definition
for an agent run having tools in a loop.
But coding agents additionally have bash, right?
So they have any kind of Linux Unix tools at their disposal and some runtime.
And there are all these sandboxes to run these different tools, etc..
But but you know, that's, that's my, my go to definition of an agent.
And that's my, my, my primitive that I'm using
for thinking about how, how I could design systems is like,
how would I embed these into my, my systems.
Okay. Very briefly about Pi
For those who don't know, it's built by Mario.
Mario Zechner out of Vienna.
So very, very minimal coding agent.
If you haven't used it please give it a try.
The minimalism is its feature,
so the way to define it, to define pi is what's not pi.
There is no MCP servers, there's no subbasins,
there's no permission pop ups, there's no plan mode.
There's no built into dos, there's no background bash thingy.
But in order to have some of these things, you can actually tell
Pi to create it, right.
So this is the I don't know. Hello world example.
Kind of like so you tell pipe, please create a Pi extension
that ask for permission when I, when I want to push the main branch to remote.
Right.
So it doesn't have permissions, it doesn't have these pop ups.
But I want now a pop up that gets up
when I'm pushing the main branch to to remote.
And it actually does this right.
So it creates these files.
Permission gates is called pre-push guards.
So it creates these typescripts and a markdown.
Here's the summary of what it has done.
And then when I push to
when I push a region to main push me to
to to a region, I actually get this pop up
right, I think allow this command to push to remote.
All this is all of a sudden now I've changed my agent to be working
exactly the way that I want to, and this is kind of like got me thinking
of how how would that change my software, my my systems.
And we're going to see this later.
So in order to motivate this a little bit
and make this more practical, I'm going to introduce you to an example.
And this is not in any type of development example.
This is an application that we've built as a prototype for a client.
And their request was that
there are quoting system takes way too long.
They get they have this after sales process
where they sell parts and the quote system.
There's an email inquiry coming in and then there's lots
of manual processing that we want to automate.
Now this is per se not
we don't need AI to solve this, but AI makes it much simpler.
And I would argue for the long run also more
more powerful.
And we can solve more use case with it.
But basically we have an email inbox which analyzes customer requests.
We check different backend systems, the CRM, etc.
and then creates quotes and drafts.
The architecture is very much.
Inspired by OpenClaw or we have some gateway.
We're routing these.
And then the way we've architecture this is we've basically created
an agent per customer where we have these different prompts.
Again think about Sol, MD etc.
but now we have it per customer and then per case.
We're creating a session.
I'm going to talk a little bit about what a session is, but think about one
agent per customer and then one session per case.
So this is a you know you know, a dashboard.
I'm not sure if you can read this, but we have basic, basic KPIs.
We have activities, we then have an email inbox.
And the way that we've we're doing this, we're basically replicating the inbox
at some point it will be based in outlook.
So the user doesn't even need to leave their tool.
But right now we're replicating the inbox.
And yeah, once an email comes in it looks for a case or creates a case.
And here you see that on top and hide side.
There's a case associated with it and we can open it.
Now the case again has KPIs and we have different.
We can look at the clients.
We have all the client information.
We have different steps for this case.
So everything is kind of like the the user understands of what's happening there.
And then we can look into the details.
And if we do this then all of a sudden
we kind of see a little bit of what's under the hood.
And again this is an early prototype.
So we'll see where this goes.
But what you can start seeing is that we now have the system prompt here.
Right.
So we're describing of what the agent is doing
of what this client specific context etc.
and then different tool definitions.
And speaking of tools,
this is usually this is more like a in-depth view.
So not a normal view for any type of user.
But here we can look into the to the
into the session and the different steps that went through the system.
And here we have different tool calls.
One is the tool call of understanding the actual state of the case.
So we have an ERP, CRM system a CRM system in this case where the state is stored.
And then we have ERP system where we're looking up the parts.
Both our external systems, both are APIs
and both are included as tools in this in this case.
And then the final result is an email draft.
So the way we're architecture in this is that we're not sending out
emails just yet.
We are drafting emails so the user can actually then afterwards
change the email, you know, to, to whatever, whatever their liking.
But the the argument is that you're much faster
and reviewing the email and then sending it.
Cool. So that's the application, right?
So again, the overall idea is coding agents are these
awesome new tools that we're seeing in the OpenClaw and other tools.
Pie is one of these agents which is an embedded and OpenClaw.
By the way.
That's not true since like two weeks.
So I need to change the title of my talk because they have just ripped out pie.
But that's yeah, the talk wouldn't be so nice, the title.
But anyway, so we have OpenClaw, we have pie embedded.
And now the question is what do we do with it.
And these are a couple of, of of primitives building blocks
right for you to reason about.
So you can take one of these and see of how you could work with this.
Okay.
So let's start with the agent setup.
The agent setup is not as simple.
And you know and also this is pie.
And you can do this with other agents.
So I'm not saying that it happened to be using pie.
But there are other SDKs you could do this with.
But Pi is a good good good starting ground.
So very simple right.
So you have these do you have different levels of SDKs?
I'm using the the coding agent SDK.
So the same thing that you're running on your desktop as a developer.
You you define the model.
You define the different tools and how to, to work
with these sessions and the different resources to load.
Speaking of resources, I'm not like usually if you start the coding
agent AGENTS.md is loaded and in this case I have a different of reusable
AGENTS.md that I'm storing and reusing through throughout the different agents.
So, you know, we have a general describing the overall business.
We have something a little bit of like task oriented and how to query the client
and more about client specific like discounts etc.
like context information.
And same goes same is true for skills, right?
So right now we're not using skills as much.
But the overall idea is the same as like we are making
sure that we control and how these skills are loaded into the system.
And that's how you put it up.
Very simple.
Not much, not that interesting,
but I just wanted to show you on how to how simple it is to get started.
So I think the first part architecturally to reason about
is like what tools do you provide to your agent?
Right.
Again, we have these general instructions and you can generate them.
And now the question is like how does this thing behave with the
with the rest of the system, which is tools, right.
So again tools you have this agent in the and and a general description.
And when you start the agent you have these you make these tools available.
And the large language model decides when to call these tools.
You start guiding them.
But at the end of the day the large language
model decides, okay, I'm going to call this this tool.
We have three tools right now K state, which is the the way of
talking with the CRM
of understanding where the overall state of these cases,
an ERP system where we do the lookup
and the email.
Now, the part
that then gets interesting when you think about how to work with
these tools, is where you actually start designing for the system
and the way that that like when, when Yvonne and myself were reasoning
about this a couple of weeks back, the way that we've,
we've phrased it is like, don't make your agent guess right.
Try to be precise about the tool definition.
Make it the intent revealing,
make it scope to the specific task.
And by the way, you can change tools on the fly, etc..
Right.
But that's where you start designing the system.
If you think about back and OpenClaw, what is the magic of Open
Claw is that it has all these different tools to it at its disposal.
Right file to understand the file definition,
whisper to translate an audio file.
And here's the same thing. Right?
You need to think about like you don't have a predefined workflow,
but instead you have these different tools that you call.
So one of the first bigger design design decisions that you do
is defining these tools.
And it's really interesting.
And there's lots of
written articles about this and you need to experiment with this.
But depending on the model and spending on how you do this, the self
revealing of how what tools are available and how to use them
is actually what the agent itself does.
You all very often see this in Pi when it actually calls the tool
with a dash help, for example, or inspects the error messages, etc.
and there's lots of things that you can start designing around it
to make your agent go do the right thing.
And obviously, well, I should tell this, but obviously
also don't hand out the tools the agent shouldn't use.
Right?
There's we actually have a tool called Data Box where we help users with this.
But this is a general pattern.
It's like people are saying, okay, don't don't use this tool.
Don't use this tool in their instructions.
But they hand it over anyway.
And then they, they, they, you know,
they are surprised that the agent deletes the, the database.
Right?
Don't be surprised if you give the agent a tool.
It's going to assume it's going to use it.
But there are some ways you can actually help.
If you are not able to define the tools or you cannot.
You don't know anything up front.
There's a couple of ways to guide the agent as well.
And these are extensions.
So there's different level of extensions.
I'm going to talk about the eventing
mechanisms in Pi where you can basically write these extensions.
And we've seen this in pi at with with pi the coding agent in the beginning.
And the example where we're listening to events, there's different types
of events, different agent life cycles, session life cycles
where we can actually basically hook in and do things.
The part that I'm going to talk about are the tool execution.
So to call two call results, this is where
most of the extensions that we've built play.
Yeah we've built.
So this is the example that I've showed before.
We have this agent with the goal.
And we're calling these tools.
And now we can ingest lifecycle hooks here.
So for example before before we do a tool call
or after we've done a tool result.
So the the idea here is we cannot control that the LM is calling it.
Right. That's the whole magic behind it.
But when when it's when it does we can actually ingest
and and filter out things or do something with the result.
Here's the example from from our system.
We have a in the draft email.
When it drafts an email we do another sanity check that
that the email is in the custom domain of the client.
So we're kind of validating the output
of of of a tool call and making sure that it does.
So far it always has been green.
But this way we are making sure. Right.
So we're not relying on the instructions,
but we can actually make sure that always the right domains.
And you can obviously do this with other validations,
all types of business logic you can put in here.
And that means that the flow of
what the agent does is us open, right.
But you can still make sure that certain systems, certain
guardrails are implemented.
Here are a couple of other examples for drafting emails.
The states.
So these are, you know, different types of examples in this use case.
And you can obviously think about your own examples.
Another part where we feel that these two calls are
helpful is actually interesting information.
Right.
So this is all about this context engineering thing
where you make sure that the agent
that the large language model gets the right amount of information and
maybe you don't want to or you cannot do all the information
upfront because maybe it's dynamic or there are other situations.
So here in this case we do we can embrace
ingest certain information that we look up as we do this.
Cool. So this is tools.
And the last primitive I want to touch on are sessions.
So this is a big part of of pie as well.
And sessions are these is these three structure
of an event log that Mario has created.
And it's actually pretty nice.
If you use the coding it's agent yourself.
And you, you wander off and you like
you know, took a detour of like, okay, this is going nowhere.
And then it's like, okay, let's get rid of all it.
It's really easy to go back. Right.
And you can do different types of, of of trees.
Right.
Go try one path and another path and you still have the whole context
with you and you can navigate around it very easily.
There's different types of, of types of information.
So this is a JSON L structure.
So you have these JSON information with messages model
changes different types of things.
And you can ingest Jones write your own custom messages which are sent to the LM
and those which are not sent to the level custom message in this case sorry.
Yeah.
Quick overview, but the the session.
So remember the way I have architected the application
is that we have a case, we have an agent container per customer.
And then we have sessions per case.
And now that we have these sessions right with, with this audit log
and with all this information, now you can we can start thinking
about other types of agents working on the same information.
We can redo certain things or change certain things because, you know,
someone has decided either manually or automatically
or doing things, or we can reuse patterns.
One of the things that we're exploring
is that we're actually
going through the session logs, and we're creating a skill out of this, right?
So we're going through the session information and creating a skill
afterwards, which we're going to do evals around it, etc..
Right.
But the point is the session, the session log is really, really powerful.
And I also think that the tree information is going to be powerful.
Although to be fair, we have not explored that too much.
All right.
Cool. So we have a couple of primitives.
I hope this gives you some ideas on how you could architecture
this this this application your your type of applications.
So let me close off with a couple of patterns or how how this
then builds into applications and flows.
So the first one is actually the workflow.
And this is the application that I've shown for before.
Right.
So the overall idea is we reuse we we give it a couple of problems.
We give it tools, we give it extensions to build these streamlined workflows.
And again I think this is going to be really, really powerful
because the agent is going to be adaptive to whatever is coming.
But that doesn't doesn't need to end there.
The other one is actually the more primitive version of this.
But as we have all these tools and this contact information,
why not give a power user a full blown chat right
where they can actually use the embedded coding agent in their system?
Right?
Think about Cowork in your system.
And now all of a sudden we are reusing
tools where we're using a context information.
Very different flows in the system.
Right. So again very much power user.
We actually don't have a user persona that is actually using this.
So this is a little bit formal formal thinking but we're using this.
The idea is that you can use this with existing sessions right.
So you can clear up existing or you can actually create brand new brand
new sessions and sessions as in cases.
Now if you keep thinking about this, about sessions, you can
and you know about the Model Context Protocol and their extension,
about MCP UIs and MCP apps, you can think about,
okay, maybe there is a something in between, right?
Maybe I'm not just only chatting with it.
Maybe I'm actually in interacting with the with a session in a different way.
Right.
So in this case here this is the parts lookup.
And we're not displaying the raw JSON anymore.
But we're we're displaying a rich interface which we can now interact with.
Right.
Change in this case change the amount of of of
what's requested for for any reason.
But it's it's like the way, the way that I'm thinking about is like
we have this general this, this, this more like application that we've built.
Then we have this chat.
And now in the chat we could start embedding more which UIs.
Right.
So it's cards at, it blends over over one or the other.
Which brings me to the final point, malleable software.
And this is a an article
by which or an essay by encode switch which I really, really like.
And it talks about this idea that software systems
should not be these predefined systems, but more of an ecosystem
where anyone can adapt their tools to their needs with minimal friction.
The example in the article in the essay is this specific,
these kitchen tools where you have this very sophisticated slicer.
I don't know if you guys still watch TV, but in Germany
we had this channel where you can you get these things all, all day long,
or you could just use a knife. Right?
But knives are adaptable.
You can do different things.
Yes. You might need a little bit training on it, but you can do different things.
And the authors of this article, they argue for software
that has not these predefined flows, but the rather
small tools that you can reuse.
The article is meanwhile adapted to the
AI flows or to this AI native world.
But the ideas are older.
But with AI, I think, and some of the patterns that I've shown,
I think we have a great deal of of potential ways of doing this.
And if you rethink about this, right, what can we
if we think about these software, these systems that we've built so far,
these building blocks that we've seen, what if what if the software
can change itself? Right. Similar to Pi. Right.
What if a user could basically just say like the extension that I've shown, right.
The extension is just a TypeScript. Right?
So why why isn't the user able to articulate that and say,
you know, only make sure that you don't send emails
which are not in the customer domain, right.
And maybe they can adapt it because of the power user.
Right? So that's that's the overall idea.
And yeah, I hope you got some inspiration.
And I'm not sure if you have any time for questions.
Yes we do. All right. Thank you very. Much
because.
Do we have any questions.
We've got one over here.
Can we get a mic over to this lady please.
Sorry, I've had to come over here because the projectors in.
The ice.
Yeah.
So you mentioned the idea of users being able to especially power users,
sort of take control and adapt the software to their needs.
How do you have any ideas on managing, I guess, the security implications of that.
So obviously, you know,
certain users can be trusted to interact with the LM
and adjust the extensions,
but I guess there's
downstream effects from that, either through
not understanding what they're doing or malice.
And yeah, that's.
Very, very great question.
No thank you.
So I think the way to think about
it is the level of freedom always needs
to stay within within certain boundaries.
So for example the you know,
we have these different tool calls where it's able to do different things.
Not sure if you realize, but the the draft, the draft email tool
is exactly designed as it is.
The system is not able to send emails.
It's only able to send draft emails.
So at the end of the day, you're in control.
You you are in control of what what it can do.
Right.
But but here, right. Again we're drafting emails.
And in this case we're saying like, you know,
do we want to do additional checks on that email. Right.
And the LM does something, but I want to do some additional checks.
And these are the kind of extensions that I'm thinking about, like certain
power users are able to like, you know, they don't care.
They just churn out these or like type different type of users.
And others are saying
starting to introduce certain guardrails or certain automations
in these type of things.
And that's that's both on the tool design level,
like you need to design the tools and then on the extensions.
But the point being is that that now
the LM can start calling these tools in any way.
Right now, all of a sudden it's like, okay, I'm going to draft an email
because there is some reason that I'm thinking about
which you have not previously thought about, but
with with these extensions, you can put another set of guardrails around it.
You're welcome.
Okay. I think we might have time for just one more.
So we've got one just here.
Matthias, I have created
an MCC Gmail MCP server, which does the same.
What's the difference between Pi and Gmail and CP server?
Great question.
First of all, great that you build your own MCP servers.
That's awesome.
No it's the the the the.
It's exactly that, right?
You have started defining the tools and now.
But the question is what do you do with these tools. Right.
So you have to find your own MCP server for Gmail that only sends you
that lets you create drafts on a Saturday afternoon, whatever.
Right.
You have like defined your special tool.
Now the question is, what do you do with it? Right.
I'm assuming you're doing this.
Where are you using it?
In some coding agent, in cloud code or or some other tool.
And this talk is, is like
first off, I think there's a future and software where, where we,
where systems are actually built around just defining these tools and guardrails.
And there's like these power users who keep using this.
Right. Coworker is one of these example.
But what I'm trying to motivate as you're starting as you have defined these MCP
tools, what if you start embedding them into a bigger software, right.
What if you start embedding them into a
an email automation tool.
And my I would argue, please have a look at Pi or some other coding
agent harness and reusing these MCP tools in order to build that software.
That's the core idea.
Okay. Well, brilliant.
Thank you very much, Matthias.
Thanks again. To the chairs.
So.